Hello, I’m going to give you a quick presentation of Jibian. First of all, we can see that on the
right we have a menu here. This is used to go back directly, close all pages, and return
to the main menu. This here is the terminal emulator. Here is where you can see all the software; we’ll
see a bit later what it’s used for. This is the file manager, which lets you see all
your files. Firefox is a web browser, Chromium as well, Thunderbird is an email client, Evolution
too, and here we have LibreOffice. At the bottom left, we can see Applications; here all the applications
are sorted and categorized. If you’re looking for a specific application, you can click
right here on the small magnifying glass, which opens a search. For example, if we search for the terminal,
hop, we find it. At the bottom right, we have other information, such as
the two screens I have, the battery, whether your microphones and speakers are enabled,
you can manage the power, see if you are connected to Wi-Fi, and the applications you are using. Here
is the update indicator. You can see that I’m up to date, but if you’re not,
you’ll have a big red warning panel, so you’ll know that you need to update.
Here you can see how much the processor is being used; this is the task manager. Here is the
date and time, and finally the user currently logged into the computer. Now I’m going to show you some
useful applications. Here we can see the two email clients, Thunderbird and Evolution. They are
more secure than webmail, and they are very practical because you can use them with
PGP keys. Now let’s look at Software. This allows you to install all kinds of
applications, games, and so on. For example, I’m going to install Lunanti. As you can see here, you can
install it directly; you just need your user password. Once the game is installed,
you just have to open it. Hop, you arrive at the test screen. I already played a demo,
so just for information, I have a computer with 4 GB of RAM, and you can see that it works very well.
I can build, I can break things. Or there’s also SuperTuxKart, a Mario Kart–style game but under a free license.
Once the game is installed, you launch it and you’ll see that you can configure everything. So here,
I’m going to play solo. You can choose your character, your difficulty level, do a normal race,
your level, the number of laps, the number of opponent karts, the driving direction. Hop, you can start,
and that’s it. And here, the game runs normally.
applications: classic LibreOffice, Calc, Draw, Impress,
Math, and Printer. You can select everything. So here, for example, I choose something and you can see
that it works the same way, but using free software. You can also see that there are other useful
programs you can install. For example, in Development, I have Code OSS, which is a derivative of VS Code
but in a free version. You can also do graphic design.
In Multimedia, for example, I have Shotcut, which is the software I
to do video editing, including the video I’m currently creating.